Notes on Running C

There’s an intro to C tutorial for beginners at
https://www.cprogramming.com/tutorial/c-tutorial.html
You might find it helpful.

You are welcome to use an IDE for C if you have it and like it. 

Otherwise:

Use your favorite programming editor to create a program. I use BBEdit on my Mac because it’s free. Notepad++ is a good free editor for Windows. (MS Word is not a programming editor!)

Here’s “Hello World” in C:

#include <stdio.h>
int main()
{
    printf( "Hello World\n" );
    return 0;
}

Save it as a .c file, such as helloWorld.c

Make sure you have a C compiler such as gcc. 
(On OSX, you must install programmer development tools (Xcode) to get a compiler; you may have already done this when you installed the OS, but it was optional.) A good way to see whether you have a compiler is by typing 
which gcc
at the command prompt. If you get nothing, you don’t have it. If you get a path, such as
/usr/bin/gcc
or something similar, you have it.

Then compile and run it from the command line:

~/CS320/Ccode: gcc helloWorld.c
~/CS320/Ccode: ./a.out

The first command compiles your code and creates an executable called a.out.
The second command runs a.out. The ./ in front of a.out tells the OS to look for a.out in your current directory. Most likely, your directory is not included in your path, so without the ./, your OS cannot find the a.out that you wish to run. 
